<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title><![CDATA[Yan Fernandes Blog]]></title>
        <description><![CDATA[This is my blog]]></description>
        <link>https://yanfer.vercel.app/</link>
        <generator>RSS for Node</generator>
        <lastBuildDate>Fri, 02 Aug 2024 00:00:10 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="https://yanfer.vercel.app//rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        <language><![CDATA[en]]></language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[How to Never Forget: Mastering the Art of Retaining Knowledge]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[


This article comes from a YouTube video titled
[I learned a system for remembering everything](https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Rvey9g0VgY0) by Matt D'Avella, a
YouTuber focused on productivity content, and Ryan Holiday, described as _"one of the world's bestselling living
philosophers"_ in his bio on Amazon.

We will pass through important insights to fix the content you can retain when reading a book.

## How to Read a Book

---

First and foremost, we really need to relearn how to read a book. When we are starting out, we often think that reading
a book simply involves spelling out words sequentially, constructing phrases, followed by paragraphs, and eventually
chapters. However, this approach is perhaps the least effective way to truly absorb and retain the content. It leads us
directly into the pitfall of the [forgetting curve](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Forgetting_curve), which is a topic I
address more thoroughly in another article.

Reading should be a positive experience, a pleasure. It's not about rushing through the material as quickly as possible.
Nobody boasts, "Dude, yesterday I had the fastest sex ever, it was awesome." If you feel like you're a slow reader and
want to pick up the pace without sacrificing comprehension, consider the approach outlined in the book
[How to Win Friends & Influence People](https://www.amazon.com/-/pt/dp/0671027034/ref=sr_1_1?sr=8-1) (I believe this is
a common feature in all editions of the book, mine being the Portuguese version from Companhia Nacional). Here's how you
can read non-fiction books and still extract valuable content:

1. Cultivate a deep and dynamic desire to learn everything the book has to offer. Approach it with a genuine hunger for
   knowledge and an eagerness to explore its insights.

2. Read each chapter at least twice before moving on to the next one.

3. While reading, take breaks to reflect on how you could apply the content to your own life. Ask yourself, "Where in my
   life could I use this information? In what types of situations?"

4. Highlighting is more crucial than you might think. Pause periodically to highlight any passages that you believe will
   be useful for future reference.

5. Start journaling. Keep a simple notebook handy and jot down any insights or lessons learned from the book, along with
   the situations they apply to and the source book.

## How to Take Notes

---

We often wonder why we should bother taking notes. Initially, it may seem like a tedious task that only prolongs the
time it takes to finish a chapter. However, it's essential to understand the purpose behind note-taking. What sets apart
a stored datum from a book and a stored datum that you'll inevitably forget? It's not about hoarding every note and
rereading them tirelessly or feeling compelled to tattoo information onto our bodies to ensure we won't forget it.

I refer to this concept as the Life Cycle of Information.

![Life Cycle of Information](https://dev-to-uploads.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/articles/znuxtt86652c2bal9297.png)

**Collect/Create:** This stage involves gathering information either by creating it yourself or collecting it from
external sources.

**Store:** Once collected, information needs to be stored in a way that is easily retrievable and comprehensible. This
might involve organizing notes in a systematic manner or utilizing mnemonic devices.

**Use:** Information serves its purpose when it is applied in relevant contexts. This stage involves actively
incorporating the stored knowledge into decision-making, problem-solving, or creative endeavors.

**Share:** Knowledge gains value when shared with others. Whether through teaching, discussing, or collaborating,
sharing information enriches collective understanding and fosters collaboration.

**Archive:** As time passes, some information may become less immediately relevant but still valuable for reference or
historical purposes. Archiving ensures that valuable insights are preserved for future use.

**Destroy:** Not all information retains its usefulness indefinitely. Some data may become outdated, irrelevant, or even
harmful. Knowing when to discard or update information is crucial for maintaining an accurate and manageable knowledge
base.

### The Analog vs Digital

In Matt D'Avella's video, Ryan Holiday suggests favoring the analog path over the digital one, arguing that it allows
for a deeper immersion in the content and enhances understanding of the book.

In this approach, after highlighting key passages in the book, we transfer the important information onto flashcards.
Subsequently, we revisit and reread the material, organizing it into categories and connections. Employing diagrams or
maps can further aid in this process.

However, as a software engineer, I believe we could utilize tools like Obsidian and Excalidraw to organize and revisit
the content we need to read, along with our note-taking system. Excalidraw could serve as a comprehensive tool for
creating diagrams or mind maps, streamlining the digital note-taking process.

## Revisit and Revise

---

At this point, we understand why we should take notes and how to take them effectively. Now, I feel that this is the
most intuitive chapter of this article. Seriously, once you have all your notes, it's faster and more efficient to
simply read through them or refer back to the book directly rather than sifting through tiny letters to find the
specific chapter you're looking for.

## Give It a Try!

---

Now that you've learned about this system for remembering everything from the books you read, why not give it a try?
Start implementing the strategies discussed in this article and see how they work for you. By taking notes effectively,
organizing your thoughts, and utilizing tools like flashcards or digital note-taking apps, you can enhance your ability
to retain and recall information from the books you've read.

Remember, it's not about completely overhauling your reading habits overnight. Start small, experiment with different
techniques, and gradually incorporate them into your routine. Over time, you'll likely find that you're retaining more
information and gaining deeper insights from your reading material than ever before.

So why wait? Start now and take advantage of the opportunity to remember everything from the books you read—or at least
more than before.
]]></description>
            <link>https://yanfer.vercel.app//blog/how-to-never-forget</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://yanfer.vercel.app//blog/how-to-never-forget</guid>
            <category><![CDATA[Obsidian]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[Zettelkasten]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[Learning]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[Books]]></category>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Yan Fernandes]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Thu, 01 Aug 2024 03:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://yanfer.vercel.app//image.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Becoming Smart: The No-Nonsense Guide]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[

You don’t need 12 years of school + 4 years of college + 6 years of graduate school to become smart. Seriously, if it took
that long, we’d all still be swinging from trees. Genetics? Meh. Habits are what really matter. So, let’s dive in.

## Why Become Smart?

For what? To get money? To impress people? Any answer works. But first, know yourself and figure out what kind of
approach you’re willing to take.

## How to Become Smart

Most advice on the internet is as useful as a screen door on a submarine. Socrates himself would have accomplished
nothing with the internet’s wisdom. Here are some gems:

- Eat fruits
- Drink coffee
- Sleep more
- Take IQ tests
- Listen to classical music

Sounds good, right? But at some point, you actually need to LEARN something.

"So what can I do to become smart?"

**Read.** Just this. But it depends on what kind of reading you do and what skills you want to achieve and improve.

- **Fiction books:** More likely to improve your vocabulary than teach you a high-income skill.
- **Non-fiction books:** You’ll understand more about how the world works in certain areas.

## How to BE Smart

If we become smart, do we need to correct other people? My answer is yes, but it’s much more important how you do this.

Take this dialogue as an example:

> **Bob:** Crazy how we evolved from chimpanzees, right? **Alice:** Well ACTUALLY, evolution is NONLINEAR, and SEVERAL
> human-like species inhabited Earth SIMULTANEOUSLY, none of which could even be REMOTELY CONSIDERED as chimpanzees.

Here, Alice just sounds arrogant. So, how can we approach this more politely?

> **Bob:** Crazy how we evolved from chimpanzees, right? **Alice:** It is crazy, right? You know, I was reading the
> other day that humans and chimpanzees share a common ancestor from 10 million years ago. Since then, we've been
> evolving separately. I always thought we evolved FROM them, but it turns out we just evolved side by side.

You can be smart and humble (and also sound like you occasionally touch grass).

The key is to teach people what you know without making them feel dumb. That way, people actually learn from you, and
you’ll be seen as a smart and respectful person.

## Where to Find These Books

You don’t need to read all five books that everyone tells you to read. Just choose a topic you want to understand. For
example:

Data Structures: Go on Google and search “data structures book,” then choose the one with the best reviews.

Books usually cost money, and for legal reasons, I always recommend you buy these books. But you might accidentally come
across a website named Library Genesis. You might accidentally search for the title of the book, click on the first
link, download a file, and open it in a proper book reader. I’m not responsible for that, feds.

## How to Use What You Read

So, now you know how to get a book (buying), and you know that this book contains skills and information to use in
conversation. Good! But how do you actually learn these skills, you ask? I have
[this other article](https://dev.to/yanpi/how-to-never-forget-mastering-the-art-of-retaining-knowledge-531h) about
retaining knowledge that will really help you.

But here are 10 fast tips to know before learning from a book:

1. No practice -> Brain forgets
2. 20% knowledge -> 80% results

And that’s it. It’s the 20% of the list.

## Some Cool Graphics

This is the [learning curve](https://www.valamis.com/hub/learning-curve):

![Learning curve graph](https://dev-to-uploads.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/articles/hwph3kar4umtqbvtyzhr.png)

As you can see, the first 20% gets you a lot of progress, but YOU NEED to practice. Books only make you smart if you
give your brain a reason to remember them.

"But can I practice while reading the book?"

Let’s suppose you’re reading a book about mechanics. You can’t change the battery of your car just because you’re
reading, right?

Ideally, you should, but you can still practice by imagining the situation. Watch a video of someone doing what you’re
studying, visualize yourself taking the same steps, and, if you can, take notes. This way, you’re telling your brain
it’s something you want to remember instead of just memorizing it.

Our school system is built on this principle. The teacher teaches you a lot of stuff you’ll never use, or if you do,
it’ll be in 10 years. To get a graduation, the teacher applies a test. If you study and practice, you get good grades;
if you don’t, you get bad grades. Or, if you’re South Korean, you go to prison (joke—you only go to prison if you
cheat).

But now we have a problem: once you’ve taken the test, there’s no need to remember that information. So how can we
remember something? To answer that, check
[this article](https://dev.to/yanpi/how-to-never-forget-mastering-the-art-of-retaining-knowledge-531h).

**disclamer**: this article is based on [this cool video](https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=C5OJJD3Eytk) from
easy,actually yt channel
]]></description>
            <link>https://yanfer.vercel.app//blog/becoming-smart-non-sense-guide</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://yanfer.vercel.app//blog/becoming-smart-non-sense-guide</guid>
            <category><![CDATA[Becoming Smart]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[Learning]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[Books]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[Productivity]]></category>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Yan Fernandes]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Wed, 31 Jul 2024 03:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://yanfer.vercel.app/undefined" length="0" type="false"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[How to start taking notes with Obsidian]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[


## Articles 
My Articles about how to start taking notes with [Obsidian](https://obsidian.md/):
- [How to Never Forget: Mastering the Art of Retaining Knowledge](https://dev.to/yanpi/how-to-never-forget-mastering-the-art-of-retaining-knowledge-531h)
- [Unleash the Power of Obsidian with GitHub: A Guide to Organizing Your Digital Brain](https://dev.to/yanpi/unleash-the-power-of-obsidian-with-github-a-guide-to-organizing-your-digital-brain-38cl)



## Videos

### Portuguese Content
_____
PT: [Como usar o Obsidian para fazer Anotações de Estudo](https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=qMfSkrGkoQ8) 

PT: [Obsidian para Iniciantes](https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=BgzRGat8WfE)

PT: [Tutorial Zettelkasten para Obsidian](https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=qtdCdYGSQBg)

### English Content
_____
EN: [Obsidian: The King of Learning Tools (FULL GUIDE + SETUP)](https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=hSTy_BInQs8&t=1s)

EN: [Form, Function, & Fun! - My Obsidian Vault Tour](https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=rAkerV8rlow)]]></description>
            <link>https://yanfer.vercel.app//blog/how-to-start-taking-notes</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://yanfer.vercel.app//blog/how-to-start-taking-notes</guid>
            <category><![CDATA[Obsidian]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[Zettelkasten]]></category>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Yan Fernandes]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Wed, 05 Jun 2024 03:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://yanfer.vercel.app//image.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[MY FIRST BLOG POST]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[


Estou gostando muito da minha produtividade criando este projeto, conseguir criar um thema de Blog para utilizar no
zettelkasten. Outra feature que gostaria de implementar é a de envio de emails, provalvemente vou utilizar o
`Nodemailer` com o `SendGrid` para enviar emails de notificação de novos posts.

Proximas coisas para trabalhar no zettelkasten são:

- Criar um diretorio para os arquivos do zettelkasten `pages/docs`
- Adicionar uma Tag de `New Item` para os arquivos que forem adicionados no diretorio de `pages/docs`
- Criar uma LandingPage pessoal ou algo do tipo para ser meu site pessoal e profissional
]]></description>
            <link>https://yanfer.vercel.app//blog/my-first-blog-post</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://yanfer.vercel.app//blog/my-first-blog-post</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Yan Fernandes]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Sat, 18 May 2024 03:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://yanfer.vercel.app/undefined" length="0" type="false"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[No title]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[{
  "*": {
    "theme": {
      "toc": false,
      "sidebar": false,
      "pagination": true,
      "typesetting": "article",
      "layout": "default",
      "breadcrumb": false
    }
  }
}
]]></description>
            <link>https://yanfer.vercel.app//blog/_meta.json</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://yanfer.vercel.app//blog/_meta.json</guid>
            <enclosure url="https://yanfer.vercel.app/undefined" length="0" type="false"/>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>